John Alden Carpenter Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
John Alden Carpenter Collection1891-1961 (bulk 1900-1949)
ML31.C34
Carpenter, John Alden, 1876-1951
around 1,700 items 12 boxes 5 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
John Alden Carpenter was an American composer. The collection contains music materials, primarily holograph manuscripts of Carpenter's songs, chamber and orchestral pieces, and dramatic works; correspondence; writings; photographs and artwork; biographical materials; certificates and honors; programs; clippings; and scrapbooks.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Carpenter, John Alden, 1876-1951--Archives.; Carpenter, John Alden, 1876-1951--Correspondence.; Carpenter, John Alden, 1876-1951--Manuscripts.; Carpenter, John Alden, 1876-1951--Photographs.; Carpenter, John Alden, 1876-1951.; Carpenter, John Alden, 1876-1951.; Carpenter, John Alden, 1876-1951. Selections.; Chadwick, G. W. (George Whitefield), 1854-1931--Correspondence.; Damrosch, Walter, 1862-1950--Correspondence.; Grainger, Percy, 1882-1961--Correspondence.; Stock, Frederick, 1872-1942--Correspondence.; Stokowski, Leopold, 1882-1977--Correspondence.
Organizations
G. Schirmer, Inc.--Correspondence.
Subjects
Composers--United States.; Costume design--United States.; Dance--Stage-setting and scenery--United States.; Music--Manuscripts.
Titles
Carpenter collection, 1891-1961
Form/Genre
Clippings (Information artifacts); Correspondence.; Photographic prints.; Programs (Documents); Scrapbooks.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Carpenter and his wife, Ellen Waller Carpenter, between 1932 and 1962.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Related Material
The Library of Congress Music Division has cataloged and shelved selected scores from the John Alden Carpenter Collection under the following call numbers: ML96.C274, ML96.5.C33, ML96.N22c, ML29c.C3, and ML96.D42. The locations are indicated in this finding aid.
In addition, the Library of Congress Music Division holds several collections that contain materials relating to John Alden Carpenter. They are: the
Aaron Copland Collection
Nicolas Slonimsky Collection
Glenn Dillard Gunn Collection
Serge Koussevitzky Archive
Artur Rodzinski Collection
Edison Sheet Music Collection
Julius Gold Collection
Adolph Bolm Collection
Jascha Heifetz Collection
Serge Diaghilev/Serge Lifar Collection
William Remsen Strickland Collection
Leonard Bernstein Collection
Federal Theatre Project Collection
Harold Spivacke Collection
Elizabeth Sprague Coolidge Foundation Collection; Damrosch-Blaine Collection; and the Percy Grainger Collection.
Access and Restrictions
The John Alden Carpenter Collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Music Division prior to visiting in order to determine whether the desired materials will be available at that time.
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Microfilm
Selected Carpenter music manuscripts have been preserved on microfilm under Music 1856, reels 1-5 and Music 1, reels 1770-1771.
Biographical Sketch
John Alden Carpenter was born Feb. 28, 1876 in Park Ridge, Illinois. His earliest musical studies were with Amy Fay and W.C.E. Seeboeck in Chicago and J.K. Paine at Harvard University, from which he graduated in 1897. Other musical studies included a few lessons with Edward Elgar in Rome in 1906 and four years of study with Bernhard Ziehn in Chicago (1908-1912), with subsequent studies under Ziehn disciple Julius Gold in the years that followed. Like his father, Carpenter was by profession in the shipping business, serving as vice-president of the family firm George B. Carpenter & Co. until he retired in 1936 to devote himself entirely to music.
Carpenter's musical compositions include both songs and orchestral concert and stage works. His earliest orchestral work, Adventures in a Perambulator, was written in 1914 and was the first of many successes. The ballet Skyscrapers (1923-1924), performed at the Metropolitan Opera House in 1926, was one of the first attempts at a literal depiction of modern American urban life, and thus has been accorded a certain historical significance. Other stage works include a "jazz pantomime" entitled Krazy Kat (1921), based on the comic strip by George Herriman, and a ballet-pantomime with Spanish overtones, The Birthday of the Infanta (1917). Carpenter was also considered an outstanding composer of songs; of particular note are the song cycles Gitanjali (1913, orchestrated 1934), a setting of a collection of poems by Rabindranath Tagore, and Water-colors (1916, orchestrated 1918), based on the writings of Confucius and other Chinese poets. Carpenter's commissions include Song of Faith (1932) for the George Washington Bicentennial in 1932, and the Elizabeth Sprague Coolidge commissions of his String Quartet (1927) and Piano Quintet (1934).
Carpenter was a highly successful composer in his day, being named a Knight of the French Legion of Honor (1921) and receiving such honors as the Gold Medal of the National Institute of Arts and Letters. He also received honorary degrees from Harvard University, Northwestern University, the University of Wisconsin, and the American Conservatory of Music.
Carpenter died Apr. 26, 1951, in Chicago.
Scope and Content Note
The John Alden Carpenter Collection spans the years 1891 to 1961 and contains music materials, correspondence, writings, photographs and artwork, certificates and honors, programs, clippings and scrapbooks. The bulk of the collection consists of musical materials, primarily holograph manuscripts of Carpenter's songs, orchestral pieces, and dramatic works. The holograph manuscripts of Carpenter's songs are perhaps the most remarkable feature of the collection, as they include not only his better-known works but also many that have never been published. Notable among these are numerous unpublished youthful works, such as "Brother," "My Red Hair," and "My Horror," as well as several songs from the cycles Gitanjali and Water-Colors. Carpenter's chamber and orchestral works are well represented also. For many works that Carpenter later arranged or revised, the collection contains both the original and at least one revision. The materials for Birthday of the Infanta, for example, consist of three full scores, including both the 1918 original and a revised version from 1949, as well as holograph changes to the 1949 revision; a holograph arrangement for piano, 4 hands (1938); the composer's reduction of the first movement vocalise, with harp and piano accompaniment; and numerous sketches. A number of the printed scores of Carpenter's music in the collection feature holograph annotations or alterations.
Carpenter's musical compositions include both songs and orchestral concert and stage works. His earliest orchestral work, Adventures in a Perambulator, was written in 1914 and was the first of many successes. The ballet Skyscrapers (1923-24), performed at the Metropolitan Opera House in 1926, was one of the first attempts at a literal depiction of modern American urban life, and thus has been accorded a certain historical significance. Other stage works include a "jazz pantomime" entitled Krazy Kat (1921), based on the comic strip by George Herriman, and a ballet-pantomime with Spanish overtones, The Birthday of the Infanta (1917). Carpenter was also considered an outstanding composer of songs; of particular note are the song cycles Gitanjali (1913, orchestrated 1934), a setting of a collection of poems by Rabindranath Tagore, and Water-colors (1916, orchestrated 1918), based on the writings of Confucius and other Chinese poets. Carpenter's commissions include Song of Faith (1932) for the George Washington Bicentennial in 1932, and the Elizabeth Sprague Coolidge commissions of his String Quartet (1927) and Piano Quintet (1934).
Selected scores are cataloged and shelved under ML96.C274, ML96.5.C33, ML96.N22c, ML29c.C3, and ML96.D42 and are indicated as such in this finding aid.
The bulk of the correspondence in the collection consists of letters from Carpenter to Ellen Borden (Mrs. John Borden, also addressed as Mrs. Waller Borden), who became Carpenter's second wife in 1933. This twenty-five year correspondence dates from approximately 1910 to 1935, and although the letters are largely personal in nature, they do contain mention of various compositions and productions. The remaining correspondence contains items to Carpenter by various colleagues and friends, including George Whitefield Chadwick, Percy Grainger, Frederick Stock, Leopold Stokowski, and Walter Damrosch. There is also considerable correspondence from the 1940's between Carpenter and his publisher, G. Schirmer.
Carpenter's writings in the collection consist primarily of his program notes for works such as Adventures in a Perambulator, Skyscrapers, The Seven Ages, and the song cycle Gitanjali, as well as the stage works Krazy Kat and The Birthday of the Infanta. Many of the typescript texts for songs and dramatic works include emendations in Carpenter's hand. Other writings include a typescript entitled The Art of the Theatre by designer Robert Edmund Jones, who worked with Carpenter on a number of his stage productions, and a humorous illustrated book by Deems Taylor entitled Moments Mousical (1949), with drawings by Walter Kumme.
Of particular note are the numerous photographs and watercolors of the sets and costumes of Carpenter's stage productions. These include photographs of the shadow puppets from Krazy Kat and of both stage designs and stagings for the Birthday of the Infanta. In addition, there are numerous ink and watercolor sketches of costume designs by Robert Edmund Jones for the Birthday of the Infanta. Two charcoal drawings of Carpenter in the collection are also by Jones.
The remainder of the collection consists of certificates and honors, a variety of biographical materials, programs, and clippings. Three large scrapbooks include not only clippings and programs but also photographs from stage productions and letters received by Carpenter.
Claudia J. Widgery, March 1993
Organization of the John Alden Carpenter Collection
The John Alden Carpenter Collection is organized in nine series:
Personal Papers, 1891-1961
Writings, circa 1913-1951
Correspondence, 1910-1940s
Music, 1904-1951
Photographs and Artwork, 1891-1961
Certificates and Honors, 1921-1961
Programs, 1913-1961
Scrapbooks, 1900-1961
Clippings, 1891-1961
http://lccn.loc.gov/2010563508
Container List
- Personal Papers, 1891-1961 (Box 1, 10)
  Biographical materials from the life of John Alden Carpenter.
  - Biographical data (manuscript and typed), including dates of compositions and data on first performances (Box-folder 1/1)
  - School report cards, 1891-1892 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Family papers, including both manuscript and typescript descriptions of Carpenter's ancestors, family histories, as well as relevant correspondence and clippings (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Coat of arms, family portraits (Box-folder 10/1)
- Writings, circa 1913-1951 (Box 1, 10)
  Carpenter's program notes for various productions, typescript texts for songs and dramatic works that include emendations in Carpenter's hand, and writings by others, including a typescript entitled The Art of the Theatre by designer Robert Edmund Jones, who worked with Carpenter on a number of his stage productions, and a humorous illustrated book by Deems Taylor entitled Moments Mousical (1949), with drawings by Walter Kumme.
  - Writings of John Alden Carpenter (Box 1, 10)
    - "A Foreword to the Wise" (manuscript) (Box-folder 1/4)
    - "Words of Wisdom" (typescript) (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Program notes on Adventures in a Perambulator (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Program notes on The Birthday of the Infanta (Box-folder 1/7)
    - Program notes on Gitanjali (Box-folder 1/8)
    - Program notes on Krazy Kat (Box-folder 1/9)
    - Program notes on The Seven Ages (Box-folder 1/10)
    - Program notes on Skyscrapers (Box-folder 10/2)
  - Writings of Others (Box 1)
    - Jones, Robert Edmund
      - The Art of the Theatre, [typescript] (Box-folder 1/11)
    - Koo, T. Z. (compiler)
      - Songs of Cathay: An anthology of songs current in various parts of China among her people Shanghai, China: The Association Press, undated (Box-folder 1/12)
    - Pierson, Thomas C.
      - John Alden Carpenter. Dissertation proposal, Eastman School of Music, Nov. 1951 (Box-folder 1/13)
    - Taylor, Deems
      - Moments Mousical. Chicago: Ziff-Davis Publishing Co., 1949, Drawings by Walter Kumme. (Box-folder 1/14)
    - Young, Stark
      - Somebody's Saint, [typescript] (Box-folder 1/15)
    - Birthday of the Infanta, text excerpts, Manuscript and typescript (Box-folder 1/16)
    - Hyacinth, incomplete text, Typescript (Box-folder 1/17)
    - Khaki Sammy, Typescript with pencil emendations in hand of Carpenter (Box-folder 1/18)
    - Song of Faith, text, Typescript with title and attribution in hand of Carpenter (Box-folder 1/19)
    - Miscellaneous poetry texts, Manuscript and typescript (Box-folder 1/20)
- Correspondence, 1910-1940s (Box 2-3)
  Includes correspondence from Carpenter to his second wife Ellen Borden and correspondence to and from Carpenter by various colleagues and friends, including a considerable amount between Carpenter and his publisher, G. Schirmer.
  - Letters from John Alden Carpenter to Ellen Carpenter (Box 2-3)
    Arranged either by category or chronologically.
    - Letters by Category
      Arranged according to categories devised by Ellen Carpenter (formerly Mrs. Waller Borden).
      - "Imagery and Humor" (Box-folder 2/1)
      - "Interest and Ideas" (Box-folder 2/2-3)
      - "Referring to Music" (Box-folder 2/4)
    - Letters by Year
      Arranged chronologically.
      - 1910-1922 (Box-folder 2/5)
      - 1923 (Box-folder 2/6-7)
      - 1924 (Box-folder 2/8-9)
      - 1925 (Box-folder 2/10-12)
      - 1926 (Box-folder 2/13)
      - 1927 (Box-folder 3/1)
      - 1928 (Box-folder 3/2)
      - 1929-1930 (Box-folder 3/3)
      - 1931-1935 (Box-folder 3/4)
      - undated (Box-folder 3/5-7)
  - Letters to John Alden Carpenter (Box 3)
    Arranged alphabetically by name.
    - American Institute of Arts and Letters see: Scrapbook, 1900-1933
    - Barrère, Georges see: Scrapbook, 1943-1961
    - Benedek, Theodore Alfred (Box-folder 3/8)
    - Biancolli, [?] (Box-folder 3/9)
    - Bloch, Joseph (Box-folder 3/10)
    - Cadman, Charles Wakefield see: Scrapbook, 1900-1933
    - Cameron, Basil see: Scrapbook, 1914-1942
    - Chadwick, George Whitefield see: Scrapbook, 1900-1933
    - Chasins, Abram (Box-folder 3/11)
    - Coolidge, Elizabeth Sprague see: Scrapbook, 1914-1942
    - Copland, Aaron (Box-folder 3/12)
    - Damrosch, Walter See also: Scrapbook, 1943-1961 (Box-folder 3/13)
    - De Lamarter, Eric see: Scrapbook, 1914-1942
    - Dumesnil, Maurice (Box-folder 3/14)
    - Engel, Carl see: Scrapbook, 1900-1933
    - Fisher, Renée B. (Box-folder 3/15)
    - Flagler, Harry H. (Box-folder 3/16)
    - G. Schirmer, Inc. (Box-folder 3/26-27)
    - Gilman, Lawrence see: Scrapbook, 1914-1942
    - Gold, Julius see: Scrapbook, 1900-1933
    - Golschmann, Vladimir See also: Scrapbook, 1914-1942 (Box-folder 3/17)
    - Grainger, Percy Aldridge See also: Scrapbook, 1943-1961 (Box-folder 3/18)
    - Gunn, Glenn Dillard see: Scrapbook, 1900-1933
    - Harvard University see: Scrapbook, 1900-1933
    - Hasselmann, C. see: Scrapbook, 1900-1933
    - Hurlbut, Byron Satterlee (Box-folder 3/18a)
    - Janssen, Werner see: Scrapbook, 1914-1942 see: Scrapbook, 1943-1961
    - Jones, Robert Edmund (Box-folder 3/19)
    - Kernochan, Marshall see: Scrapbook, 1914-1942
    - Kindler, Hans (Box-folder 3/20)
    - Koussevitzky, Serge see: Scrapbook, 1943-1961
    - Lewis, [John?] Hamilton see: Scrapbook, 1900-1933
    - MacKinnon, Douglas A. (Box-folder 3/21)
    - Massine, Leonide (Box-folder 3/22)
    - Mueller, Herb (Box-folder 3/23)
    - N., "Hump" T. (Box-folder 3/24)
    - Piatigorsky, Gregor see: Scrapbook, 1943-1961
    - Rodzinski, Artur see: Scrapbook, 1943-1961
    - Roosevelt, Franklin Delano (Box-folder 3/25)
    - Schirmer, G. see G. Schirmer, Inc.
    - Serkin, Rudolf, (to Mrs. Carpenter) (Box-folder 3/28)
    - Sousa, John Philip see: Scrapbook, 1943-1961
    - Stock, Frederick A. See also: Scrapbook, 1914-1942 (Box-folder 3/29)
    - Stokowski, Leopold See also: Scrapbook, 1943-1961 See also: Degree certificates from: American Conservatory of Music, Chicago, IL (Box-folder 3/30)
    - Stone, John Timothy see: Scrapbook, 1914-1942
    - Swarthout, Gladys (Box-folder 3/31)
    - U. S. George Washington Bicentennial Commission see: Scrapbook, 1914-1942
    - University of Rochester See also: Scrapbook, 1943-1961 (Box-folder 3/32)
    - Walter, Bruno see: Scrapbook, 1914-1942
    - Young, Steve see: Scrapbook, 1900-1933
    - Ziehn, Bernard see: Scrapbook, 1900-1933
    - Ziehn, Emma see: Scrapbook, 1900-1933
- Music, 1904-1951 (Box 4-9, 12)
  Includes primarily holograph manuscripts of Carpenter's songs, chamber and orchestral pieces, and dramatic works. Many of his printed scores feature holograph annotations or alterations.
  Selected scores are cataloged and shelved under ML96.C274, ML96.5.C33, ML96.N22c, ML29c.C3, and ML96.D42 and are indicated as such in this finding aid.
  - Manuscripts, 1913-1949 (Box 4-8, 12)
    Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - About my garden, Holograph score; [2] p. (Box-folder 4/1)
      MUSIC 1856 (reel 4, item 57)
    - Ad domnulam suam, Holograph score, incomplete; [1] p.; On p. 1: May 1913. (Box-folder 4/2)
      MUSIC 1856 (reel 5, item 58)
    - Adventures in a perambulator, Holograph score, revised version; 105 p.; see ML96.C274
      MUSIC 1856 (reel 1, item 1)
    - Adventures in a perambulator, Holograph piano score, incomplete; [8] p. (Box-folder 4/3)
    - Aged woman, Holograph score; [2] p.; On p. 1: Feb. 7-15 (Box-folder 4/4)
    - America the beautiful, Holograph score; [1] p.; On p. 1: Sunday, May 27-28 (Box-folder 4/5)
    - The anxious bugler, Holograph full score; 26 p.; At end: Beverly, Aug. '43; see ML96.C274
    - Berceuse, Holograph piano score, incomplete; [4] p. (Box-folder 4/6)
      MUSIC 1856 (reel 5, item 62)
    - Berceuse, Holograph full score; 32 p. (Box-folder 4/7)
      MUSIC 1856 (reel 3, item 38)
    - The birthday of the infanta, Holograph full score, with emendations in red and blue pencil; [184] p.; see ML96.C274
      MUSIC 1856 (reel 1, item 3)
    - The birthday of the infanta, Holograph sketch, condensed score; [20], 44, [6] p.; At end of p. 44: Finished 8/20/18; see ML96.C274
      MUSIC 1856 (reel 1, item 4)
    - The birthday of the infanta; arr., Holograph score for piano, 4 hands, in ink and photocopy; 44 p.; At end: This revision 1938.; see ML96.C274
      MUSIC 1856 (reel 1, item 5)
    - The birthday of the infanta; arr., Holograph piano score; 45 p.; see ML96.C274
      MUSIC 1856 (reel 1, item 6)
    - The birthday of the infanta. Suite, no. 2, Holograph full score; 60 p.; see ML96.C274
      MUSIC 1856 (reel 1, item 7)
    - The birthday of the infanta. Suite, no. 2 See also: Sketches of the symphony no. 1, The birthday of the infanta, and an unidentified instrumental piece. 191- ] (Mfm.# 3/34), Holograph full score, in ink and part photocopy; 60 p.; At end: This arrangement 1949. Chicago and Carmel, Calif.; Inserted: two copies of the composer's reduction of the vocalise in the 1st movement, with harp and piano acc. (4 p. each); Laid in: Changes in orchestral score and parts by the composer in ink (7 p.); see ML96.C274
      MUSIC 1856 (reel 1, item 8)
    - Blue gal, Holograph piano-vocal score; 3 p.; On t.p.: 1st version. 1941.; At end: Nov. '41 Chicago; Laid in: Holograph sketch with additional verses (1 l.); see ML96.C274
      MUSIC 1856 (reel 3, item 39)
    - Blue gal; arr., Holograph full score; 16 p.; Arranged for mezzo-soprano & orchestra; At end: May '43; Laid in: typescript of text; see ML96.C274
      MUSIC 1856 (reel 3, item 40)
    - Bright truth is still our leader, Holograph piano-vocal score; [1] p. (Box-folder 4/8)
    - Brother, Holograph piano-vocal score in purple pencil; 3 p. (Box-folder 4/9)
    - Canterbury bells, Holograph piano-vocal score; 1 p. (oversize) (Box-folder 12/1)
    - Carmel concerto, Holograph, in ink, with corrections in pencil; 45 p.; At end: Jan. to June '48. Carmel, Chicago, Beverly.; see ML96.C274
      MUSIC 1856 (reel 1, item 9)
    - Chanson d'automne, Holograph piano-vocal score; [3] p. (Box-folder 4/10)
    - Les cheminées rouges, Holograph piano-vocal score; [10] p.; On p. 1: Feb. 1922 (Box-folder 4/11)
    - Les cheminées rouges See also: Le petit cimetière, Holograph piano-vocal score; 6 p.; At end: 11/14/34 (Box-folder 4/12)
    - Chevaux de bois, Holograph piano-vocal score, incomplete; [4] p. (Box-folder 4/13)
    - Le ciel, Holograph piano-vocal sketch; 2 p.; At end: John darling, do not forget your wife over seas. I will return. Bless you. Hazel. (Box-folder 4/14)
    - The cock shall crow, Holograph piano-vocal score; [3] p. (Box-folder 4/15)
    - Cold song, Holograph piano-vocal score; [3] p. (Box-folder 4/16)
    - Come, Copyist's piano-vocal score; 6 p.; On t.p.: June 1914 (Box-folder 4/17)
    - Concertino, piano, Holograph full score, in ink, with blue and red pencil additions and corrections; 80 p.; see ML96.C274
      MUSIC 1856 (reel 1, item 10)
    - Concertino, piano, Holograph two-piano score, incomplete; p. 17-58 (Box-folder 4/18)
    - Concertino, piano. New York: G. Schirmer, 1920, Printed two-piano score, with emendations in red ink; 65 p.; On p. 1, in red ink: Revised 1949; Laid in: holograph list of changes and corrections to be made in two-piano score; 2 p.; Laid in: multiple copies (positive & negative) of optional cuts for p. 58-9 (Box-folder 4/19)
    - Concertino, piano See also: Unidentified sketches, miscellaneous (Mfm.# 5/66), Holograph short score of cadenza (optional); [4] p.; see ML96.C274
      MUSIC 1856 (reel 1, item 11)
    - Concerto, violin, Holograph full score; 52 p.; At end: Eze-Beverly, March-September '36; see ML96.C274
      MUSIC 1856 (reel 1, item 12)
    - Concerto, violin; arr., Holograph score, with corrected sections (partly photocopy), pasted in; 23 p.; Arranged for violin & piano; At end: Eze Village-Beverly, March-Sept. 1936; see ML96.C274
    - The cryin' blues see: Jazz boys see: Shake your brown feet, honey
    - Dance suite, Holograph full score; 13, 18, 28 p.; At end of 1st movement.: Feb. '43; At end of 2nd movement.: March '43; see ML96.C274
      MUSIC 1856 (reel 1, item 13)
    - Dansons la gigue!, Holograph piano-vocal sketch (fragment): [1] p. (Box-folder 4/20)
    - Danza, Holograph piano score; 5 p.; On t.p.: Original piano score; At end: August '35. Pride's Crossing.; see ML96.C274
      MUSIC 1856 (reel 5, item 60)
    - Danza, Photocopy of holograph piano score; 5 p.; see ML96.5.C33
    - Dawn in India, Holograph piano-vocal score; [2] p. (2 copies) (Box-folder 4/21)
    - Discontent, Holograph piano-vocal score in purple pencil; [2] p. (Box-folder 4/22)
    - Ditty, Holograph piano-vocal score in purple pencil; [2] p. (Box-folder 4/23)
    - Don't ceäre, Copyist's piano-vocal score; 7 p. (Box-folder 4/24)
    - Dutch dance, Copyist's piano score; 4 p. (Box-folder 4/25)
      MUSIC 1856 (reel 5, item 61)
    - En sourdine, Holograph piano-vocal score; 4 p. (Box-folder 4/26)
    - En sourdine, Holograph piano-vocal sketch; [4] p. (Box-folder 4/26)
    - Endlose Liebe, Holograph piano-vocal score; [2] p.; see ML96.C274